Guide to the Carl Carlson Papers, 1937 - 1941
Carl Carlson Papers, 1937 - 1941
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Carlson, Carl, 1920-1943.
1000-132
1.0
3
Carl Carlson was a Wesleyan University student between 1937 and 1941 but did not graduate. He was killed in World War II.
The Carl Carlson Papers contain Wesleyan course work, prose and poetry by Carlson, and correspondence.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Professor Fred B. Millett was temporarily in charge of Carlson's books, papers and manuscripts until 1976. The Carl Carlson Papers came out of the larger Fred B. Millett Papers.
Biographical Note
Carl Carlson was born May 3, 1920 in Hartford, CT. Carlson was in the first group of Fox Scholars selected in 1937, the same year Lewis Fox, an attorney and philanthropist of Hartford, CT established the Fox Foundation. The Fox Foundation provided scholarships for outstanding high school seniors to attend college. Carlson attended Wesleyan University September 1937 to February 1940 and September 1940 to June 1941. He was a non-graduating member of the class of 1941. Carlson joined the Royal Canadian Air Force and served as an aerial navigator until he was killed in action in the European Theatre of Operations December 1, 1943.
Collection Overview
Series 1 contains course notes, notebooks and written papers regarding Carlson's classes while a student at Wesleyan University. Series 2 consists of Carlson's writings. Series 3 contains a published version of Carlson's poems and correspondence by and about Carl Carlson. Most items are undated but are from the 1937-1941 period.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Carlson, Carl, 1920-1943.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.; American poetry--20th century.; Soldiers’ writings, American.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Wesleyan University Course Notes and Papers
  - Greek and Latin Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Notecards
    - Spiral notebook
    - Chronological outline
  - Greek Literature and Philosophy, undated (Folder 2)
    - Alexandrian Poets Influence on Roman Literature
    - Apuleius
    - Apollo
    - Ethics of Epicurus with footnotes and bibliography
    - Two Greek Romances
  - Aristophanes, Metaphysical Poet, June 4, 1938 (Folder 3)
  - Aristotle on Drama, undated (Folder 4)
  - Petronius, undated spiral notebook (Folder 5)
  - Varro and the Menippean Satires, undated (Folder 6)
  - Vergil (Folder 7)
    - Notes
    - The Culex
  - Diabolos, undated (Folder 8)
    - Statement of Purpose and Outline (typescript and handwritten)
    - Manuscripts on Satan
    - Faith (typescript)
    - Satan in the Middle-Ages
    - Alchemy
    - Bible; Withcraft In (typescript and handwritten)
    - Notes on witchcraft, werewolf, Lilith and Demonology
  - Compact With the Devil (Folder 9)
    - Bibliography
    - Typescript manuscript
    - Notes; 2 pink student journals and other papers
  - Book Lists (Folder 10)
  - Astronomy 2: Some Aspects of the Martian Question, June 1939 (Folder 11)
  - English 13 and 14: Richard II and Antony (Folder 12)
  - English 45 (Folder 13)
    - Cat in the Rain, evaluation, October 1940
    - Aristotle, Poetics and Synge, Riders to the Sea, September 1940
    - Eagle and the Mole, January 1941
    - The 'Greatness' of Poetry: An Opinion, January 1941
  - Philosophy 3 and 4 (Folder 14)
    - Plato's Theory of Ideas, December 1939
    - The Bases of the Kantian Doctrine of the Beautiful, June 1941
  - Greek 11 and 12 (Folder 15)
    - Aristophanes as Critic, June 1938
    - The Electra of Sophacles, March 1939
    - Euripides Hippolytus, May 1939
    - Note cards
  - On Poetry (Folder 16)
    - A Note on the Translation of Poetry
    - An Identification of Poetry, December 1940
    - Nature of Poetry
    - Functions of Poetry
  - On Tragedy (Folder 17)
    - The Origin of Tragedy, January 1938
    - Dionysos and Greek Tragedy
    - A Note on Dionysos Melanigis
    - A Note on the Orphic Dionysis
    - War and Tragedy
    - The Senecan Influence on Elizabethan Tragedy
  - The Alexander Romance (Folder 18)
  - Bona Socientas, Philosophia, Satanasia (Folder 19)
  - Philosophy (Folder 20)
    - Definitions
    - Dogmatics on Censorship
    - 2 spiral notebooks and sheets of notes
- Writings by Carl Carlson
  These materials are non-course related.
  - Chutney: 3 notebooks and loose papers (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Note: Chutney is possibly a short story and this folder contains 6 partial versions.
  - Prose - Miscellaneous (Folder 2)
    - Death of a Potential Liberal
    - Art Colony
    - Miscellaneous short writings
  - Prose - Short Stories (Folder 3)
    - Spiral notebook containing Picar, Primavera, Meditatio ad Meam Matreum, and Praefatio Libello
    - Nick Manacchio
    - Prelude to Mass
    - The Son/The Mother
    - Death in the Barbershop
    - Dark of the Moon
    - Gotha
    - Death in the Coal Mine
    - Murder Without Motive
    - Untitled writings
  - Untitled play (Folder 4)
  - Poetry
    - Loose pages (Folder 5)
    - Seven journals of poetry (Folder 6)
    - Carl Carlson Poems (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Note: 80 pages of handwritten poems
    - Carl Carlson: Selected Poems, copies 1, 2 and 3 (Folder 2)
      Note: 113 sheets of typed poems
    - Notebook I (Folder 3)
      Note: Over 90 pages of Carl Carlson poems, typed or hand-written taken from a notebook. NB-I and sequential page number on each sheet.
    - Notebook II (Folder 4)
      Note: Over 129 pages of Carl Carlson poems, typed or hand-written taken from a notebook. NB-II and sequential page number on each sheet.
    - Dance Macabre (poem) (Folder 5)
- Publication and Correspondence
  - Carl Carlson correspondence to Lewis Fox (Folder 6)
  - The Poems of Carl Carlson, edited by Stephen A. Kezerian '44 (Folder 7)
  - Stephen Kezerian '44 correspondence regarding Carl Carlson (Folder 8)
  - Fred Millett correspondence regarding Carl Carlson his books and papers (Folder 9)